Finding Aid for the Olive Percival Papers LSC.0119
UCLA Library Special Collections
Olive Percival papers
circa 1869-1948
UCLA Library Special Collections
Percival, Olive
LSC.0119
22.0 linear feet (44 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Olive May Graves Percival (1869-1945) was an avid collector of books, hats, dolls, daguerreotypes, silver, textiles, quilts, fans, bookplates, Lalique, and Oriental art. The collection consists of correspondence, photographs, negatives, scrapbooks, guest books, typescripts of articles and poems, bookmarks, bookplates, and material relating to Percival's collection of children's books.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Olive Percival left her collections to various friends and her will benefited several institutions at the time of her death. The remainder of her estate was sold at an auction in 1946. Additional Percival materials at UCLA include the Olive Percival Collection of Children's Books in the Department of Special Collections (purchased from Ernest Dawson) and Percival's volumes of 17th and 18th century literature in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.
Gift of Florence Moore Kreider, 1949-50.
Gift of Jane Wright, 1949-50.
Gift of Theresa Levy, 1949.
Gift of Hortense Goldwater, 1949.
Gift of Mrs. Kirby, 1949.
Gift of Pauline Curran, 1949.
Gift of Marjorie Van Deusen, 1950.
Gift of Mrs. Morris Cohn, 1949 & 1954.
Gift of Mrs. Henry B. Pflueger, 1950.
Gift of Ward Ritchie, 1950 & 1959.
Gift of Dawson's Book Shop, 1983.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9927227663606533
Biography
Olive May Graves Percival was born July 1, 1869, near Sheffield, Illinois; moved to Los Angeles, California, with her mother and sisters, 1887; worked as an insurance clerk in Los Angeles; an avid collector, Percival amassed ten thousand books as well as other collections of hats, dolls, daguerreotypes, silver, textiles, quilts, fans, bookplates, Lalique, and Oriental art; her cottage home was situated along the Arroyo Seco east of Los Angeles; died February 19, 1945.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, photographs, negatives, scrapbooks, guest books, typescripts of articles and poems, bookmarks, and bookplates of Los Angeles author and bibliophile Olive Percival. Also includes material relating to Percival's collection of children's books. Includes a microfilm copy (17 reels) of her diaries and a typescript, held at The Huntington Library in San Marino, California.
Expanded Scope and Content
This index is the result of an exploratory examination of Olive Percival Collection of Children's Books, acquired by purchase for the University of California at Los Angeles Library in August 1946. This is the first inventory taken of the collection, preparatory to its normal processing routine.
The collection represents the personal hobby of Miss Olive Percival, first woman real estate agent of Los Angeles, and reflects her personality as revealing as a private diary. The intense love which she bestowed on these nostalgic mementos of her own childhood days, is evident from the notations penciled in many of the books, and in the artistic protective covers and book marks which she made for them.
Consisting of 527 titles and a total of 540 items, the collection spans two centuries of children's literature, from the earliest publication, Politeuphuia wits common-wealth (1707) to the 1914 edition of Walter Crane's Sleeping Beauty and Blue Beard. The main strength of the collection concentrates on the approximate period from 1790-1840, and the majority of titles are of British publication. (The exact date of initial acquisition of these books cannot be exactly determined, but it is evident that Miss Percival did not add any books after 1931).
Some of the books had strong association value for Miss Percival. We find some of her own school books, and various volumes presented to her by members of her immediate family and friends, which, though of no great intrinsic value, must have been of great sentimental value to her.
(In the absence of corroboration, it is difficult to determine what standards, if any, Miss Percival set for herself). An examination of the titles listed in Darton's chapter on children's books in the Cambridge History of English Literature will reveal that most of those titles are present in the collection, and therefore constitutes a valuable core, about which an ever-expanding supplementation can be made. Represented in her library are the works of most of the notable writers for children in the period covered. The works of Bodlsmith, Watts, More, Sherwood, Turner, Trimmer, Barbauld, Edgeworth, Dorset, the Taylors, Lamb, Cameron, Hughes, Howitt, Abbott and William T. Adams (Oliver Optic), and Peter Parley, are included.
There are notable absences in the gathering of the great. There are no works by Lewis Carroll, Walter Scott, the Brothers Grimm, Charles Kingsley, Andrew Lang, Robert Louis Stevenson, or Priscilla Wakefield. Though Thomas and John Bewick add to the rarity of the collection, there is only one volume illustrated by Randolph Caldecott, and not by Kate Greenaway.
The content of the collection may be divided into several types of children's books. The moralistic and didactic literature of the 1790s to 1840s dominates the collection, as even a glance at the titles will indicate. Apart from this general group, but not entirely escaping its tone, is the vast amount of poetry. In a strict sense, this must be regarded as verse, and doggerel verse for the most part, since few poets of the period deigned to prostitute the Muse for an audience of mere children. It is evident that poetry must have been one of Miss Percival's main interests. Miss Miriam Fine has prepared a descriptive bibliography of those books devoted in their entirety to poetry, but there are many others which include selections of both prose and verse. This interest in poetry carries over into the religious hymns and songs, represented by Isaac Watts, Philip Doddridge and the New England primers. In the third group must be placed the numerous alphabet books, readers, and school books which represent the nostalgic interest of Miss Percival in her own school days.
Chapbooks, those ephemeral, quickly-produced and eagerly sought after little pamphlets, are present in a large proportion to the total collection. Some of them served to keep alive the imaginative delight of children in the wonderful and fanciful, in a period of dominating moral didacticism. They did not escape entirely; too many perverted the story of adventure and fairyland to a moral purpose.
Since so much of the literature represented in the Percival collection is of an anonymous or pseudonymous nature, I have prepared an author and title index, in the hope that it may be of use to future research workers. Annotations will be found under the author entry. Several books which were included in the lot, because of their small size or for some other undiscovered reason, have been found to be unsuitable for a collection of children's literature, and have been placed in an appendix.
Holdings described in either Cumuchian or Rosenbach are referred to by their catalogue number (either G or R) in the annotations. There these holdings have been fully described in either catalogue, no attempt has been made to duplicate the descriptions. Rather, an effort has been made to supplement or corroborate them. In several cases, items in the collection have been brought to light inaccuracies in Gumuchian, especially in regard to first editions. The annotations for these items are devoted mainly to describing similarities or differences in format. Many books need little or no annotation; their title supply enough information as to content. Relevant quotations by Miss Percival have been included.
At the top right hand corner of each sheet has been placed a dating symbol, consisting of the first three letters of the author's surname, the date of publication, and an A if the book was published in the United States. By rearranging the sheets, a chronological listing of the items is possible. I admit the effectiveness of this device is hampered by the lack of dates for many of the items, especially the elusive chapbooks.
In exploring the collection, one distinct problem presented itself. Should a complete and thorough bibliographic job be done on only a few items, or should the whole collection be inventoried completely? Time was a governing factor in the decision. Knowing how eager the library staff was to have this inventory taken, so that the books could become available for research, I determined to finish the entire inventory, and to try to complete as much bibliographical identification as possible. For this identification, much detective work was done in the bibliographical tools of the library, and in the works listed at the end of this preface. Since there has never been any definitive bibliography of children's literature, the information had to be gleaned from diverse sources, and it is obvious that there are other sources still untapped. So I cannot claim completeness of identification for this inventory.
In conclusion, I should like to reiterate that I believe the strength of this collection consists in the inclusion of the principal writers of an important period in the development of a literature for children. Although the very rare books included are relatively small in number, they will serve to correct existing inaccuracies concerning first editions. The entire collection would be extremely difficult to assemble piecemeal from the rare book market of today.
I would recommend that the small collection of children's books in the possession of the William Andrews Clark Library, as yet unaccessioned, should be added to the Olive Percival collection, if this is administratively possible. This would strengthen the larger collection, and bring all children's books to one central point of consultation.
The Olive Percival collection offers research students a rich store of information, in the study of literature for children; in the historical study of customs, dress and social life; in a study of the influence of adult literature on children's books, and, conversely, the influence of childhood reading on the works of the great writers, and in the history of educational theory and practice.
Robert R. Hertel, English 200; June 1947.
Related Material
Bookplate Collection (Collection 144). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Women book collectors -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Authors, American -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Percival, Olive -- Archives
- 1. Biographical data.
  - Notices of Miss Percival's death., Item 1; Four newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Small folder detailing memorial services for Miss Percival, February 22, 1945.; Item 2 (Box 1)
  - Small folder of biographical data, published by Ward Ritchie Press., Item 3 (Box 1)
    General note
    [Probably printed with "Yellowing Ivy."]
  - Folder regarding Miss Percival and her collection of children's books., Item 4 (Box 1)
    Published by the Library, University of California, Los Angeles,
    Scope and Contents note
    Also, one (1) copy of The Bridge, v.2, April 27, 1948, no. 6, containing a reprint of the above item.
  - Letter. Seth W [?] Cushman (Secretary, Society of Mayflower Descendants in the State of California) to Miss Ella Rae Briggs (attorney at law), San Francisco., 1945, Mar. 8.; Item 5; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: death of Olive G. Percival.
  - "Olive Percival - A Tribute,", Item 6; Typescript on three sheets (8 1/2 × 11) (Box 1)
    Signed in ink on p. 3 by Mrs. George Veach Wright, dated May 22, 1945.
    Envelope addressed to Mrs. S. L. Kreider. Marked copy of the program of the Friday Morning Club for May-June, 1945, indicating May 22 -- Poetry Day in commemoration of Miss Percival.
  - "Olive Percival - A Tribute,", Item 7; Typescript on three sheets (8 1/2 × 11) (Box 1)
    Includes a note of transmittal on blue note paper, and envelope addressed to Mrs. S. L. Kreider.
  - Letter. Robert R. Hertel to Mrs. Florence Kreider., 1947, Aug. 16.; Item 8; Envelope. TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: return of two items borrowed by Mr. Hertel in preparation of an article on Miss Percival.
  - Excerpts from an article "In Quest of the Perfect Bookplate" by Clare Ryan Talbot, Item 9; Typescript, one sheet (8 1/2 × 11) (Box 1)
    Re: Olive Percival's interest in bookplates.
  - Excerpts from an article "Historic California Bookplates" by Clare Ryan Talbot, Item 10; Typescript, three sheets (8 1/2 × 11) (Box 1)
    Re: Olive Percival's collection of bookplates.
  - Events in OP's childhood -, 1868 - 1874.; Item 11; Typed sheet (blue carbon) (Box 1)
    See also 5. Personal Notes, Item 4.
  - Florence [Kreider] to Mrs. Wright., 1940 Dec. 24.; Item 12; ALS, 1 p. note paper folded. (Box 1)
    Letter mentions OP.
  - Florence [Kreider] to "Dear Friend" [Mrs. Wright]., Item 13; ANS, on white card. (Box 1)
    Mentions Miss Percival.
  - Peggy" to "Mother dear" [Mrs. Wright?]., [n.d.] "; Item 14; Written in pencil on three sheets of white paper. (Box 1)
    Tells of OP's illness.
  - Dwight Gibbs to Mrs. Wright., 1944 Nov. 14.; Item 15; Written on picture postcard of Huntington Memorial Hospital, Pasadena. ANS. (Box 1)
    Re: OP's condition.
  - Mira C. Saunders to Mrs. Wright., 1944 Nov. 26.; Item 16; ALS, 1 p. fnp. (Box 1)
    Re: OP's room at the Carter Rest Home, Pasadena, etc.
  - Florence [Kreider] to "Dear Friend" [Mrs. Wright]., [1945?] July 4.; Item 17; ALS, 1 p. folded. (Box 1)
    Re: article of tribute to OP.
    See also Box 1, Items 6-7;Box 12, Item 6.
  - Ella Rae Briggs to "Legatees under the Will of Olive Percival, deceased.", 1945 Mar. 26.; Item 18; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: bequests.
  - Reprint from L.A. Daily Journal Notice of Hearing of Petition for Probate of Will and Codicil.", dated March 26, 1945 "; Item 19 (Box 1)
  - Postcard announcing sale of OP's collections, Item 20 (Box 1)
    Printed postcard addressed in ink to Mrs. Geo. V. Wright by Michael M. Weisz, Auctioneer.
  - Postcard announcing final sale of OP estate., Item 21 (Box 1)
    Postcard addressed to Mrs. Geo. V. Wright announcing final sale on August 12, 1945 of OP estate. Written in ink, signed by Michael M. Weisz, Auctioneer.
  - Ella Rae Briggs to Mrs. Jane Wright., 1946 Feb. 22.; Item 22; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: delivery of bequests.
  - Disposition of property., 1941 July 1.; Item 23; Reproduction of typescript. [16] leaves. (Box 1)
    Gift of Dawson's Book Shop, September 14, 1983
- 2. Material on children's books, book lists, etc.
  [See also 12. Miscellaneous, Item 7: Material on McGuffey.]
  - Dawson's Book Shop. Flowers and gardens; books for sale, September 1947.; Item 1; 2 copies. (Box 1)
    Features books from Olive Percival's collection.
  - Publishers' Weekly, v. 151, no.13, Mar. 29, 1947.; Item 2 (Box 1)
    Item marked re. D. A.S.W. Rosenbach's gift of children's books to the Free Library of Philadelphia.
  - Fletcher, Ifan Kyrle. Children's books offered for sale... Catalogue 90. London, 1946.; Item 3 (Box 1)
  - Edwards, H. W. Early books for children. No. 24. Newbury, Berks, England, 1945.; Item 4 (Box 1)
    Separated Materials note
    [Transferred to Children's Books Catalogs ?Z1037E124 - WJS 1/9/69]
  - Chiswick Book Shop. Rare books. Catalogue 20. New York, n.d.; Item 5; OP signature, pencil, top first page. (Box 1)
    (Added to collection 9/30/48.)
  - Mott, Howard S. Jr. First Editions, American and English. Catalogue Three. New York, Item 6; Small label with design of lily and initials "OP" pasted on cover. (Box 1)
    (Added to collection 10/5/48.)
  - Milne, A.A. A Reader's guide. Books for children. London, Cambridge University Press, 1948.; Item 7; 24 pages. Pink paper cover. 21.5 cm. (Box 1)
    Gift of LCP.
  - Children's Books of Yesterday. Elkin Mathews Ltd. Takeley, Bishop's Stortford, Herts., Item 8 (Box 1)
- 3. Correspondence
  - Home Insurance Company correspondence., Item 1 (Box 1)
    Miss Percival kept the following letters together in an envelope with a brief record of her employment and a memo: "Someday may these serve me as memos for a story of the business world." [Received at UCLA in an envelope marked by OP "Keep"]
    - 1. Envelope. Postmarked City Hall Sta., N.Y., Mar. 11, 1929.
      This envelope contained the following correspondence.
      - 2. Memo card. Identification of the following correspondence, by OP.
      - 3. [Elbridge G. Snow] (President, The Home Insurance Company) to Olive Percival. New York., 1908 Dec. 3.; TLS, 1 p.
        Re: Salary of $1700 per annum for 1909.
      - 4. Olive Percival to Margaret [Fowler]. Los Angeles., 1929 Jan.22.; TLS (carbon copy), 1 p.
        Note on back in OP's hand, ink: "To Margaret Fowler 22 Jany., 1929. She died 13 July, 1931. Alice Willard brot me to her service. Alice. d."
      - 5. Olive Percival to [Wilfred] Kurth. Los Angeles., 1929 Mar. 4.; ALS (copy), 1 p.
        Re: resignation effective April 5, and suggestion that a pension would be welcome.
      - 6. W[ilfred] Kurth (Vice President, The Home Insurance Company) to Olive Percival. New York., 1929 Mar. 11; TLS, 1 p.
        Re: acceptance of OP's resignation.
      - 7. [Wilfred] Kurth (Vice President, The Home Insurance Company) to Olive Percival. New York., 1929 Apr. 3. "; TLS, 1 p.
        Re: decision of Executive Committee to recommend pension salary of $150.
      - 8. Olive Percival to Wilfred Kurth. Los Angeles., 1929 Apr. 10.; ALS (cc), 1 p.
        Re: appreciation for presenting pension question.
      - 9. Olive Percival to Wilfred Kurth. Los Angeles., 1929 May 14.; ALS(copy), 1 p.
        Re: congratulations on promotion. Pencil note by OP on letter: "Mr. Kurth - Elected President of The Home 1929."
  - Lizzie Peake to [James]. Dover [England]. To: "My dear Cousin." Date supplied later., [1891] Dec. 23.; Item 2 (Box 1)
    Note on letter in another hand: "Yellow shoe strings." ALS, 1 p. [Included in a misc. envelope with some book dealers' catalogs, clippings, etc.]
  - [Olive Percival] to Mrs. []. Frick. Los Angeles. TL (cc), 1912 Nov. 21.; Item 3; 1 p. and 5 p. enclosure. (Box 1)
    Re: garden books. Enclosure: List of garden books, 5 p.
  - Ray I. [?] Hibbs (Corresponding Secretary, West Philadelphia Junior Shakespeare Club) to Olive Percival. Philadelphia, Pa. Envelope postmarked Philadelphia, Pa., 1921 Apr. 15. Apr. 15, 1921.; Item 4; TLS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    [In packet "Concerning the Publishing of Miss Percival's books" which was in envelope "OP's friends, 1940-1944"].
  - W.M.S. [Wilbur Macey Stone] to Olive Percival. [n.p.], 1922 Aug. 16.; Item 5; AL, 1 p. (Box 1)
    To: [Dear Little Playmate." Unsigned, but in same hand as letter from "Wilbur" to OP dated Feb. 3, 1923. [included in a misc. envelope with some book dealers' catalogs, clippings, etc.]
  - Wilbur [Macey Stone] to Olive Percival. [n.p.], 1923 Feb. 3, Sunday.; Item 6; AL, 1 p. (Box 1)
    To: "Dear Olive." See also letter from W.M.S. dated Aug. 16, 1922. [Included in a misc. envelope with some book dealers' catalogs, clippings, etc.]
  - J[ohn] B. Bolles (Asst. Secretary, The Travelers Bank & Trust Co., Hartford, Connecticut)to Olive Percival. Hartford, Conn., 1927 Apr. 19.; Item 7; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Letter transmitting check for $5,000 covering bequest of Julia A. Graves [cousin of OP]
  - [Olive Percival] to John B. Bolles, in reply to his of Apr. 19. Los Angeles., 1927 Apr. 25.; Item 8; TL (carbon copy), 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: acknowledgment of check for $5,000 bequeathed to OP by her cousin, Julia A. Graves.
  - Grace [Pullen Ormsby] to Olive Percival. [South Pasadena, Calif.], [1928 Jan. 16]; Item 9; AL, 2 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "Dearest Playmate." Envelope postmarked Los Angeles, Jan. 16, 1928. Note on envelope in pencil: "The last place Mother-darling went." [In envelope "Olive P's friends 1940-1944"]
  - Janet M. Henderson to Olive Percival. [Los Angeles.], [1928] Feb. 14.; Item 10; ALS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "My dear Olive." Envelope postmarked Los Angeles, Feb. 15, 1928. Name "Janet Henderson" on envelope in OP's hand. [In envelope "OP's friends 1940-1944.]
  - G[eorge] R. Ranney to Olive Percival. Chicago., 1931 Feb. 26.; Item 11; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: gift of Margaret B. Fowler of $500. Note at bottom of letter, ink, in OP's hand: "Dear Margaret Fowler died 13 July, 1931-"
  - M. R. Harrington (Curator, The Southwest Museum) to Olive Percival. Los Angeles., 1932 Dec. 23.; Item 12; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Re: acknowledgment of a gift from OP to the museum.
  - Frances E. Watkins (Asst. Curator, The Southwest Museum) to Olive Percival., 1933 Jan. 26.; Item 13; TLS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    Los Angeles. Re: enclosure of deeds of gift.
  - Leda [ ] to Olive Percival. La Jolla, Calif., [1941] Jan. 31.; Item 14; ALS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "Dear Olive Percival." Envelope postmarked La Jolla, Calif. Feb. 4, 1941. [In envelope "OP's friends 1940-1944.]
  - Ethel Kurth to Olive Percival. [Ridgewood, N.J.], [1941 Aug. 5]; Item 15 (Box 1)
    To: "My dear Miss Percival." Mentions enclosures. Envelope postmarked Ridgewood, N.J., Aug. 5, 1941. ALS, 1 p., with cover. [In envelope "OP's friends 1940-1944."]
  - Isabel [Lockwood] to Olive Percival. Pasadena, Calif. Post card. Postmarked Pasadena, [1942] Apr. 7. Apr. 8, 1942.; Item 16; Postcard, autograph. (Box 1)
    [In envelope "OP's friends 1940-1944."]
  - Hanford N. Lockwood to Olive Percival. Pasadena, Calif., 1943 Dec. 29.; Item 17; No envelope. ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
    To: "Dear cousin Olive." Note at end by OP, pencil: "Aet. 82 or 93?" [In envelope "OP's friends 1940-1944."]
  - Alfred Percival Smith to Olive Percival. Philadelphia, Pa., 1927 Dec. 30.; Item 18; ALS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "Dear Cousin Olive:"
  - Alfred Percival Smith to Olive Percival. Philadelphia, Pa., 1928 Apr. 16.; Item 19; ALS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "My dear Cousin Olive:"
  - Alfred Percival Smith to Olive Percival. Philadelphia, Pa., 1928 June 13.; Item 20; TLS, 1 p., with cover. (Box 1)
    To: "My dear Cousin Olive:" Encl. newspaper clipping.
  - ACS, "Olive" to Mrs. Lemuel Goldwater. Postmarked Los Angeles, [1923] April 30, 1923; Item 21 (Box 1)
  - Note, AS on pink card, Olive Percival to "Dearest Hortense" [Mrs. Lemuel Goldwater]., 1934 Dec. 14.; Item 22; Decorated on reverse with two paper dolls held behind a paper strip, and three silver stars. No cover. (Box 1)
  - Birthday card, "Olive" to "Hortense dear-" [Mrs. Lemuel Goldwater], with note written by OP. In cover, postmarked Los Angeles, [1954 May 1] May 1, 1943.; Item 23 (Box 1)
  - Note written on small green paper: "Place-cards created for Hortense/By/`Georgette-Poiret-Matisse!' ", [n.d.]; Item 24 (Box 1)
    Enclosing 5 tan cards decorated with cut and pasted colored paper in designs of ladies. Cover addressed: "For/Mrs. Lemuel Goldwater/..." with Christmas seal on reverse.
  - Undated notes., Item 25 (Box 1)
    [Gift of Mrs. George V. Wright, May 2, 1949.]
    - a. Christmas card - green on white.
      "Olive" written in ink on front. A note to "Jane Darling" signed "Olive" in ink on back.
    - b. Small folder "A gift on Valentine's Day"